<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="hindustani_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>

<book>
    <p>
        <s>
            <o>Маълуми Шумо бод, ки камина Муҳаммадҷон писари Ҳоҷӣ Мулло Рустам дар санаи 1310 ҳиҷрӣ
                мутобиқ ба с. 1892 мулодӣ дар деҳаи Чорбоғ - наздикии оромгоҳи Хӯҷа Муҳаммадҷон Валӣ
                воқеъ дар музофоти Хӯқанд чашм ба олам кушода, тарбия ёфтааст.</o>
            <t>May it be known that the humble Muhammad-jan, son of Hojji Mulla Rustam, was born and
                raised in the village of Charbagh, near the shrine of Khoja Muhammad-jan Wali,
                located near Khoqand.</t>
        </s>
    </p>
    <p>
        <s>
            <o>Бино ба ҳикояи қиблагоҳам, он кас дар шаҳрҳои Хӯқанд ва Самарканд таҳсили улум
                кардаанд.</o>
            <t>Based on the stories told by my father, he studied in the cities of Khujand and
                Samarqand</t>
            <c>The author has in mind madrasa-level study, not primary schooling.</c>
        </s>
        <s>
            <o>Ман аз ишон <ref>Фарзи айн</ref> у <ref>Фиқҳи кайдоӣ</ref> инчунин аз
                    <ref>Мухтасар</ref> то Китоби никоҳ-ро омӯхтам.</o>
            <t>My father taught me the Farzi-i Ayn, the Fiqh-i Kidani, and the Mukhtasar (up to the
                book on marriage).</t>
            <c>By Фиқҳи қайдоӣ the author /or transcriber must have in mind the Fiqh-i Kidani, a
                14th-century work of jurisprudence. These works were part of the Central Asian
                madrasa curriculum: see Pickett, Polymaths of Islam, pp.</c>

        </s>
        <s>
            <o>Барои қорӣ шуданам шавқу ҳаваси зиёде доштанд.</o>
            <t>My father greatly desired that I become a Qur'an reciter.</t>
        </s>
        <s>
            <o>Дар ин хусус гуфта буданд: Ҳангоми таҳсилам дар Хӯканд дар моҳи Рамазон дар мадраса
                хатим сурат гирифт.</o>
            <t>In this regard (my father) once told me that while he was studying in Khoqand in the
                month of Ramadan he had begun to recite the entire Qur'an in the madrasa.</t>
        </s>
        <s>
            <o>Як қорӣ ба қироъати хатм машғул шуд, ки хеле хушовоз ва номаш Муҳаммадҷон-қорӣ
                будааст.</o>
            <t>Another student was also engaged in reciting the entire Qur'an who had a lovely
                voice, and his name was Muhammad-jan Qari.</t>
        </s>
        <s>
            <o>Ман ба Худо аҳд кардам, ки агар зан гирам ва Худо ба ман писар диҳад, номашро
                Муҳаммадҷон монда, қорӣ хоҳам кард.</o>
            <t>My father vowed to God that if he takes a wife and is granted a son, he would name
                him Muhammad-jan and make him a Qur'an reciter.</t>
        </s>
        <s>
            <o>Худои таъоло мувофиқи талабам ба ман чунин бахтро насиб гардонд, ки як марди
                соҳибкирому бузургвор маро аз мадраса <pg no="116"/> бурда, духтарашро никоҳ карда
                дод.</o>
            <t>God Almighty granted my father's request with such fortune that a great man took me from the
                madrasa and gave me his daughter's hand in marriage.</t>
        </s>
        <s>
            <o>Бо иродаи Худованд ту ба дунё омадӣ.</o>
            <t>And, according to my father, this is how I (Hindustani) came into the world.</t>
        </s>

    </p>
    <p>
        <s>
          <o>Хулласи калом, маро дар ҳаштсолагиам ба равоншод Муҳаммадалӣ-корӣ вобаста карданд, ки он шахс аз деҳаи Ҷалабир буданд.</o>
          <t>In short, at the age of eight I was entrusted (for edcutational training) over to Muhammad Ali Qari (now deceased), who was from the village of Jalabir.</t>
        </s>
        <s>
          <o>Ин деҳа аз ҷои мо дар як километр масофа воқеъ буд.</o>
          <t>>This village (i.e. Jalabir) was located one kilometer from our home.</t>
        </s>
        <s>
          <o>Дар як моҳ <ref>Ҳаятяк</ref>-ро ба итмом расондам.</o>
          <t>>I completed Haftyak in one month.</t>
        </s>
        <s>
          <o>Қорӣ-домулло аз олам гузаштанд.</o>
          <t>>Then Muhammad Ali Qori passed away.</t>
        </s>
        <s>
          <o>Падарам маро ба Тошболта-қорӣ супурданд.</o>
          <t>>My father then sent me to Tashbalta-qari (for training).</t>
        </s>
        <s>
          <o>Дар назди ин Қорӣ-домулло чор сол машғули таҳсил будам, вале ҳифзи <ref>Қуръон</ref> бароям мушкил гардид.</o>
          <t>I studied under this instructor for four years, but memorizing the Quran proved difficult.</t>
        </s>
        <s>
          <o>Ба қиблагоҳам гуфтам: Маро ба шаҳр баред.</o>
          <t>To my father I said: take me to the city</t>
        </s>
        <s>
          <o>Дар ин ҷо одам шуданам ба гумон аст.</o>
          <t>Here I fear that I would never become a (learned) man.</t>
        </s>
    </p>
    <p>
      <s>
        <o>Ин суханам ба қиблагоҳам ҳам писанд афтод.</o>
        <t>My words also pleased my father.</t>
      </s>
      <s>
        <o>То шаҳрми Хӯқанд ҳашт километр буд.</o>
        <t>(Our village) was located eight kilometers from Khoqand.</t>
      </s>
      <s>
        <o>Дар он замон кӯчаҳо вайрон, одамон бо аспу хар ва пиёда мегаштанд.</o>
        <t>At that time the roads were ruined and people traveled either by foot or by horse.</t>
      </s>
      <s>
        <o>Падарам аспе доштанд, ки аз хар каме калон маро ба пушти аспашон савор карданд.</o>
        <t>My father had a horse, which was a bit larger than a donkey, and put me on it's back and sent me off.</t>
      </s>
      <s>
        <o>Баъди ду километр гаштан асп аз лойи кӯча нагузашт.</o>
        <t>After two kilometers mud prevented the horse from traversing the road.</t>
      </s>
      <s>
        <o>Ҳарчанд қиблагоҳ занҷир заданд ҳам, нашуд.</o>
        <t>Even though my father struck (the horse) with a chain, nothing came of it.</t>
      </s>
      <s>
        <o>Аз асп фаромада, кашидем ҳам нарафт.</o>
        <t>(My father) got off the horse and pulled, but the horse did not proceed.</t>
      </s>
      <s>
        <o>Ҳайрон мондем.</o>
        <t>We were surprised.</t>
      </s>
      <s>
        <o>Ногоҳ аз қафо доду фарёди занона ба гӯш расид.</o>
        <t>Suddenly from behind us we heard a woman's shouting.</t>
      </s>
      <s>
        <o>Нигарем ба сӯи мо зане давиди меояд.</o>
        <t>Looking to our side, (we saw that) a women was coming toward us.</t>
      </s>
      <s>
        <o>Баъди наздик омадан маълум шуд, ки модарам будааст.</o>
        <t>As she approached it became clear that she was my mother.</t>
      </s>
      <s>
        <o>Қуръонро фаромӯш карда будаам, аз қафо модарам гирифта давидаанд.</o>
        <t>I had forgotton my Quran, so my mother had taken it and ran after us.</t>
      </s>
      <s>
        <o>Баъди расидан беҳолу бемадор ба замин афтоданд.</o>
        <t>When she caught up with us my mother collapsed to the ground, completely out of sorts.</t>
        <c>bē-madār is a play on words; although it is etymologically Arabic and therefore unrelated to mādar ('mother'), they sound similar. The wording here is similar to verses of Persian poetry, such as this couplet by Nasir Khusraw: ای مادر فرزندخوار ای بی قرار ای بی مدار. ناصرخسرو</c>
      </s>
      <s>
        <o>Баъди Қуръонро гирифтем, аспро кашидем, ки ба роҳ даромад.</o>
        <t>After that we took the Quran and pulled the horse on to the road.</t>
      </s>
      <s>
        <o>Қиблаҳгоҳ гуфтанд: Агар асп намеистод модарат то шаҳр медавид.</o>
        <t>My father said: If the horse had not stopped, your mother would have run all the way to the city.</t>
      </s>
    </p>
    <p>
      <s>
        <o>Хуллас, қиблагоҳ маро ба Зикриё қорӣ супурданд.</o>
        <t>Ultimately, my father entrusted me to Zikriya-qari</t>
      </s>
      <s>
        <o>Дар ин қорихона дар ду сол 14 Қуръонро ҳифз кардам.</o>
        <t>In this school I memorized 14 (parts of) the Quran in two years.</t>
        <c>The Quran is traditionally divided into 30 sections (juzʾ in Arabic, pāra in Persian).</c>
      </s>
      <s>
        <o>Мувофиқи одат қиблагоҳамон ҳамаи уламоро ҷамъ карда, тӯи хатм гузарониданд.</o>
        <t>In accordance with custom, my father assembled all of the Ulama and held a celebration.</t>
        <c>The term to'y is used in modern Uzbek to refer to wedding celebrations.
      </s>
      <s>
        <o>Аз ҳамашон барои идомаи таҳсил фотеҳа гирифтам.</o>
        <t>I received a Fatiha from each of them to bless the continuation of my study.</t>
      </s>
      <s>
        <o>Сонӣ ҳузури Мулло Эшонқул ба хондани дарсҳои ибтидоӣ шурӯъ кардам.</o>
        <t>Then I began my beginning-level formal studies in the presence of Mulla Eshanqul.</t>
      </s>
      <s>
        <o>Имлму сарфу наҳв барин китобҳои аввалро хонда, <ref>Шарҳи Ҷоми</ref>-ро сар кардам.</o>
        <t>I began studying grammar and syntax, starting with Sharh-i Jami (check translation, check reference)</t>
      </s>
      <s>
        <o>Аз ҷавониам ба илмуомӯзӣ иштиёқманд будам.</o>
        <t>My youth made me eager to learn.</t>
      </s>
      <s>
        <o>Як моҳ пеш аз Рамазон барои <pg no="118"/> такрори Қуръон ба Шоҳимардон мерафтам, ки он вақтҳо одамон бо ароба ба зиёрат раҳсипор мегардиданд.</o>
        <t>One month before Ramadan I went to Shahimardan for the purposes of practicing Quranic recitation, joining the people who were setting out in horse carts to visit him.</t>
      </s>
      <s>
        <o></o>
        <t></t>
      </s>
    </p>
</book>
